[Music]
my name is Cheryl destaso and I'm the
coordinator for the Fort Collins
Community Action Network strength
through peace is the sponsor of today's
program and they're an affiliate of the
Fort Collins Community Action Network
the grandson of Greek immigrants John
kyaku was born in Western pH
Pennsylvania through his grandparents
John became steeped in Depression era
politics developing not only a keen
sense of the injustices that plagued
American workers but also a thirst for
other cultures John earned a degree in
Middle Eastern studies from George
Washington University where he became
fluent in Greek after graduating he
continued at George Washington entering
a master's program in legislative
affairs one of John's professors in
graduate school was a CIA Spotter and
asked John to apply to the CIA which he
did early in his career John became
fluent in Arabic in the late 90s he
spent a few years in Greece and narrowly
escaped an assassination attempt by the
radical group 17 November the attempt
instead claimed the life of a British
defense
atache in 2002 John was the chief
counterterrorist operations for the CIA
in Pakistan where he led a successful
mission to to capture abuabu at at the
time thought to be al-qaeda's thirdd
ranking leader two years later John left
the CIA he worked as a senior
investigator for the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee and then as
counterterrorism consultant for ABC News
in 2007 John disclosed details about the
US torture program in an interview with
ABC News within days the US justice
department began an aggressive
investigation of John kyaku that spanned
5 years continuing through Obama's first
turn in 2012 John was arrested and
indicted on three counts of violating
the 1917 Espionage Act John and his wife
at the time a CIA agent both both lost
their jobs John's legal defense Bill
cost a million dollars which left them
with massive debt to avoid risking a
lengthy prison sentence and a million
more in debt John accepted a deal and
guilty to disclosing the name of a CIA
operative to a journalist he was
sentenced to 30 months in prison even
though the name of the operative was
never released to the public John
entered the Laredo federal prison in
February 2013 and served almost two
years he was released to house arrest a
year ago in February and finally freed
in June today John works as an
associative fell as an associate fellow
at the Washington based think tank for
policy studies John's traveled 65
countries in 43 States and this is his
first trip to Colorado for Collins
please join me in welcoming John
kyaku thank you thank you thank you very
much thank you so much I'm I'm very
happy to be
here I'm embarrassed to say it's my
first trip to Colorado I actually used
to tell people sure I've been to
Colorado cuz I went through the airport
once on the way to Santa Fe
well thank you very much uh to to
strength through peace first of all for
for having me here today U I'm very
pleased to be here and I'd like to talk
about a couple different things I hate
being the torture guy I never really
considered myself to be the torture guy
but this is the position I've found
myself in but more than torture I'd also
like to talk about ethics and
intelligence operations because frankly
there aren't any ethics and intelligence
operations so I'd like to start by
talking about Abu
Zeda I had been in the CIA for about 12
years uh before I had even heard of Abu
Zeda I spent the first seven and a half
years of my career as an analyst working
on Iraq uh mostly in the Middle East I
spent a couple of years in Bahrain I
served in Kuwait and Saudi Arabia and uh
and really worked on Iraqi issues all
those years but I got bored and in the
late 1990s I I switched I made a very
unusual switch to counterterrorism
operations and found after going through
the training that I actually had a knack
for it uh the job really is simple to
describe it's hard to actually carry out
but the job of a CIA case officer or
operations officer is to recruit spies
to steal Secrets easy is that or to
recruit spice to infiltrate terrorist
groups on your behalf now there's a lot
of work that goes into that but it's
doable and like I said I I found that I
had a knack for it and I enjoyed myself
very
much so after the September 11th attacks
like everybody else in the building I
volunteered to go to Afghanistan to do
what I didn't know and I didn't frankly
care but everybody was volunteering and
I thought that it was my patriotic duty
to volunteer as well after all I spoke
Arabic and I was one of only about a
dozen and a half people in the entire
CIA who spoke Arabic if you could
imagine such a thing um but they they
didn't send me to Afghanistan so I kept
threatening and begging and threatening
and finally they said all right they
were just tired of hearing it you can go
to Pakistan I said okay when tomorrow I
said okay what do you want me to do
there we want you to be the chief of
counterterrorism operations I said great
well I had never been the chief of
counterterrorism operations anywhere let
alone in
Pakistan right after September 11th so I
flew to Pakistan the next day and um
introduced myself to the we're not
allowed to say station Chief uh we say
the senior Cia officer in country I
introduced myself to this senior Cia
officer and he said okay welcome what I
want you to do is I want you to come up
with a standard operating procedure for
taking down a terrorist safe house I
said okay well I didn't even know where
to begin so I sat down at a desk with a
legal pad and I thought so what would I
do if I were to take down a terrorist
Safe House well I guess I'd want it to
be dark so like the middle of the night
I wouldn't want anybody to see me and
frankly I would want the terrorist to be
sleeping so I wrote 0200 at the top of
the page and I came up little by little
with his plan and um our Pakistani
Partners I'll call them uh said that
they thought they had found a safe house
where somebody was was HED up and I said
okay well let's let's hit it so we went
out at 2:00 in the morning it was about
a half a dozen of us we had a battering
ram and we broke down the door and there
was a 19-year-old Tunisian kid in there
and he started crying and asking for his
mother and that was my first Al-Qaeda
fighter this became a
pattern I came face to face with
Al-Qaeda many many times and almost to a
man they were
children um mostly teenagers or people
in their early
20s and they they had several things in
common and this really was the very
start of a transition in my thinking
about Al-Qaeda and about Islamic
terrorism they were all
illiterate they were all um jobless and
indeed had no job skills of any kind
they were all from isolated villages in
their home countries Yemen Algeria Saudi
Arabia Libya Syria all over the place
but from these very isolated Villages
nobody was from any of the big
cities I never understood this next one
none of them had good relationships with
their fathers which I thought was
fascinating but I'm not a psychologist
so I I was never really clear on what
that meant in the greater scheme of
things and um invariably the The Village
Imam would go up to these guys and say
what what are you doing here in this
Village you can't read and write you
have no job you have no future no man
would let his daughter marry somebody
like you you should go make Jihad
against the Americans because if you do
we'll give you $50 a month and if you're
martyred we'll give your family
$500 so what you're going to do is
you're going to take this ticket and
you're going to fly to Dubai and when
you get to Dubai somebody will meet you
and they'll give you a ticket to Karachi
Pakistan in Karachi somebody will pick
you up and take you to a safe house and
then finally we'll get you to a training
camp in Afghanistan and you can
train well these guys didn't have any
beef against the United States they
didn't know the Quran they couldn't read
they didn't know what the prayers were
they weren't particularly religious they
just simply didn't have anything else to
do and they didn't have any future in
their own countries and believe me
making $50 a month carrying out Jihad
against the Americans is better than
sitting in that Village in Yemen just
watching your life pass
by so they went to Pakistan
and they were young and inexperienced
and stupid and confused and when we
started bombing Tabora they all ran down
the mountain and cross the border into
Pakistan and we caught
them well that was going pretty well
because we would hit a house two houses
a night and we're catching one at a time
two five at a time one night I think we
caught eight so I thought well this is
actually going pretty well and then we
get word that Abu
was somewhere in Pakistan and my orders
were he's somewhere in Pakistan you have
to catch him and take him alive the
problem was was though that that
Pakistan is the size of Texas and it has
230 million people in it so to say he's
somewhere in Pakistan go catch him if an
impossible
Prospect we would get these cables from
headquarters um that were meant to be
helpful he's in laor he's in F Abad he
went back to lore again we think he went
back to filad again we know from his
diaries that we captured um he was just
driving back and forth between the two
cities and he was looking for a safe
house he couldn't find one that he liked
and so he was just looking around
driving around neighborhoods back and
forth that's why we couldn't catch him
so I came up with a couple of terrible
ideas ideas that just were impossible
and doomed to fail and headquarters
again was trying to be helpful and they
was they would send us these panicked
emails in the middle of the night saying
we found what we think is his safe house
it's a it's a mud uh building and it's
reinforced with three- foot thick mud
walls and these are the geoc coordinates
and we would get a team together as
quickly as we could and we would drive
over there at 2 a.m. and it was the
maternity hospital the first night and
then the second night it was the police
station so I had to say to headquarters
we appreciate you trying to help us but
please stop you we're wasting all this
this Manpower let us figure this out in
the meantime send us an analyst who can
help us go through this information and
help us find the
guy so they sent an analyst out an
analyst called a targeting analyst most
analysts sit in their cubicles at CIA
headquarters they read all Source
information everything from press to CIA
reports to Military and FBI reports
State Department cables NSA intercepts
everything and they they think these big
thoughts thoughts they figure out what
it means for policy and then they send
the their reports to the president the
secretaries of state and defense and the
chairman of the National Security
Council and the chairman of the Joint
Chiefs of Staff a targeting analyst is
somebody who's very tactical and very
operational so he'll come and go through
a stack of documents or information this
high and figure out how we can Target
different individuals so this targeting
Analyst job was to narrow down abu's
possible
locations as best he could to make
it possible for us to find him well the
analyst worked on this for several weeks
and then came to me and said I can't get
it down any lower than 14 possible sites
and I said wow we've never hit more than
two places in a single night before we
can't hit 14 so I sent a cable to
headquarters and I said we need a huge
team one big enough to hit 14 sites I'm
multaneously we need weapons and
Communications gear and night vision
goggles and battering rams and
ammunition and you name it and they
chartered a 737 and put these pallets of
equipment on the 737 and sent us a team
of 36 men half CIA half FBI FBI because
at the time you'll recall September 11th
was still an open criminal investigation
as if we were going to actually
prosecute somebody rather than just to
stick him in a secret prison or in
Guantanamo for the rest of his life
without facing any
charges so the team arrived and um we
did a lot of leg work and
pre-operational surveillance we looked
at all these different sites to make
sure that it wasn't a setup we weren't
you know going to go in and be ambushed
there was Ingress and egress and there
were a couple of mistakes we made in
this in this uh targeting of the 14
sites one of the sites was a shishkabob
stand that had a pay phone
and there were obviously Al-Qaeda people
living in the neighborhood they would go
to the shishco Bob stand make a phone
call on the pay phone and then go back
to their little hiding place well you
can't attack the shishkabob stand at 2
o'cl in the morning there's nobody in it
another one uh was a girl school that we
actually did raid and made a terrible
mistake I'll tell you that in a minute
so in one night March 28th 2002 we hit
all 14 sites
simultaneously and in the last site the
14th site we found
abua when we began to break down the
door he his bodyguard and a Syrian bomb
maker climbed to the roof of the house
and attempted to jump to the roof of the
next door neighbor's house to try to
escape there was a Pakistani policeman
on the ground in between the two houses
and he shot each of them as they were
jumping the Syrian jumped first and was
killed instantly uh Abu Zeda jumped
second and was shot in the thigh the
groin and the stomach again with an
AK-47 and The Bodyguard jumped third and
was shot through the femur nearly lost
his leg in the
end
so I asked the Pakistani when I finally
got onto onto the site I was at the
nearby Safe House our safe house I asked
the Pakistani where's where's the guy we
never told the pakistanis who we were
going after we said he was a big fish
but we were afraid that they would uh
leak it to him that we were on to him
and we were looking for him we didn't we
didn't trust them uh frankly frankly so
we called him the big fish and then that
became Mr fish so I said where is he and
he says here here's your man Mr Fish and
I looked at him all we had had was a
six-year-old passport photo of
abuaba handsome young thin beard and
mustache this guy was a fat slob clean
shaven wild Albert Einstein hair going
all over the place I said that that's
not him at least I don't think it's him
he said yes this is him this is your Mr
fish so I called the analyst I said what
do I do I said they shot somebody but
and they say it's him but I don't know
if it's him he he said get me a picture
of his eye we'll do a retinal scan so I
kneeled down over him and I shouted uh
if the hunic open your eyes but he was
dying he was bleeding to death and he
couldn't open his eyes and when I opened
his eyes they were just rolled back in
his head all you could see were the
whites so I said all I see are whites I
think he's bleeding to death and he said
get me a picture of his ear I didn't
know until that night that no two people
on earth have the same ears they're like
fingerprints so I took a picture of his
ear that this was the days before our
phones had cameras so I had to actually
pull out a camera take a picture of his
ear plug the camera into the phone
download the picture into the phone and
then send it to the analyst he sent it
to headquarters and a minute later they
came back and they said it's
him so we threw him into the back of a
filthy Toyota pickup truck that the
Pakistan Dan had commandeered and we
rushed him to the most horrible place on
Earth fad
hospital we we arrived by now it's about
3:15 a.m. there were dogs and cats
walking up and down the Halls swarms of
mosquitoes just feeding on people's open
wounds they had this bar of Irish Spring
soap with about a dozen syringes coming
out of it and if you needed a shot they
would pull the syringe out fill it with
whatever medicine you needed give you
the shot and then stick it back in the
bar of soap
again so here we are a half a dozen
Americans dressed as pakistanis in the
middle of the night with an Arab who's
bleeding to death and I told the doctor
you've got to save this guy's life in
English he was a little shocked but they
took him into the operating room and
then tried to patch them up as best they
could in the meantime word got around
the al-Qaeda community that had gotten
him and so they began driving by the
hospital and just opening fire on the
hospital I said to the Pakistani major I
was with if they realize that we're
unarmed we're dead we have to get out of
here I said can you find a a helicopter
and he said he could 20 minutes later a
helicopter landed in the parking lot and
I just walked into the operating room
and I said doc wrap it up we have to get
them on a helicopter and get out of here
so the doctor sewed him closed as
quickly as he could we loaded him onto
the helicopter and took him to a nearby
Pakistani military base he was in a coma
for the first 24 hours but during that
24-hour period I received orders from
headquarters that I was to not leave his
side the order was 247 CIA eyes on do
not leave his bedside but I was afraid I
was going to fall asleep so I tore up a
sheet and I tied him to the bed in the
meantime they took him back into surgery
to finish this operation he was bleeding
so profusely I mean he was just soaked
in blood we were soaked in blood there
was blood pooling on the ground
underneath the bed and the pakistanis
were pumping as much fresh blood into
him as as they could but it was just
leaking right out again from his wounds
so the Pakistan doctor came out and told
me I've never seen wounds this severe
where the patient lived and I said what
you got to try your best because my
orders were to take him alive we didn't
think your man was going to shoot him
three times um but they saved
him he was in this coma again for a
while I mean never really came out of it
even before surgery so it was another 12
hours or so in in the meantime um I was
very dirty you know this had been an
operation that was ongoing and we didn't
have a chance to sleep or eat or get
changed or anything so I called a
colleague of mine and I said could you
do me a favor at the safe house could
you get me a clean pair of underwear and
um and a shirt I said I'm really dirty
and I got to get out of these clothes so
he brought me pair of underwear a pair
of socks and the only clean shirt I had
was a a t-shirt that my children had
given me that I slept in it was a red
t-shirt with a decal of SpongeBob Square
Pants in the in the
middle so about six hours after that I
noticed Abu zua is beginning to
stir so I got up and I stood at the foot
of his bed like this and I was looking
at him
and I I recount this in my book that you
could see the exact instant where he
realized oh my God the Americans had me
because he opened one eye and he looked
at
SpongeBob and his pulse went from 110 to
220 and the heart monitor started
going and then the doctor ran in and it
clear and they shock him and then they
gave him Demerol and then he was out
again so I sat back down for about 4
hours I remember turning the ceiling fan
on full blast so that the mosquitoes
wouldn't wouldn't Converge on his
gunshot wounds I have a thing about
mosquitoes my wife laughs about me but I
consider myself to be a pretty tough guy
but I'm freaked out at the thought of
something drinking my blood it just is
from when I was a little kid it's always
bothered me and just to see the millions
of mosquitoes in the room and they're
all going after his wounds it just it
was disgusting so I turned the ceiling
fan on full blast to blow the mosquitoes
away from his wounds and frankly to keep
them off myself so I I waited there at
the bedside and he finally came around
again and remember I had him strapped
down on the bed like this so he looked
at me and he went like this for me to
come next to him so I went up close to
him and I moved his oxygen mask and I
said um shme what is your
name and he shook his head so I said it
again shme and he said to me in English
I will not speak to you in God's
language and I said that's okay abua we
know who you are and he said he started
to cry and he said kill me brother
please take the pillow and kill me and I
said no we've been looking for you for a
long time uh nobody's going to kill you
as a matter of fact you're going to get
the best medical care that the American
government can
provide so
he really started crying pretty hard I
think about this a lot even though it's
been 14 years I still think about it all
the time he said that he would never
know the touch of a woman he would never
know the joy of fatherhood he didn't
want to attack the United States on
September 11th he wanted to attack
Israel but he was
overruled and um after a while he
started reciting poetry that we later
found in his Diaries he wanted to talk
about the differences between Islam and
Christianity
and then I felt like we had enough of a
rapport that I said I'm going to give
you some
advice I said I am the nicest guy that
you're going to meet in this experience
my colleagues are not as nice as I am if
there's one thing you do it should be to
cooperate and he said you seem like a
nice man but you're the enemy and I'll
never Co
cooperate I said well suit yourself he
was very worried later on about what was
going to happen to him and I said I'll
tell you the truth I have no idea what's
going to happen to you nobody has said
anything to
me uh I know that they're coming to get
you I know that there's a trauma surgeon
on the plane I know that you're going to
be well taken care of but beyond that I
can't imagine that the rest of your life
is going to be
easy well the plane landed I had been
with him for 56 hours at that point and
he asked me to hold his hand while we
wielded him out onto the tarmac um I did
he was weeping quietly and we maneuvered
him onto the plane we laid him across
the luggage rack strapped the luggage
rack to the uh or strapped the gurnie to
the luggage rack and I wished him the
best and he went
on 6 weeks later I returned to CIA
headquarters
I happened to be in the cafeteria one
day and a senior officer from the cia's
counterterrorism center approached me
and said I'm glad I ran into you I
wanted to ask you do you want to be
certified in the use of enhanced
interrogation techniques I said what's
that mean enhanced interrogation
techniques I had never heard the term
before and very excitedly he said we're
going to start getting rough with these
guys and I said what's that mean
rough so he laid out to me the 10
techniques
that eventually became the cia's torture
program and I said that sounds like a
torture program how's that legal we have
laws against torture in this country oh
no no it's been approved by the justice
department it's all legal I said I don't
think this is for me you know you know
what let me think about it for an hour I
said well I had a a friend on the
7eventh floor the executive floor of the
CIA he had become one of the senior most
officers in the agency I had worked for
him in the Middle East a decade earlier
so I went up and and made a a quick
appointment to speak with him and I said
they just asked me if I wanted to be
certified in these enhanced
interrogation techniques what do you
think of this and he said first let's
call it what it is they can use whatever
euphemism they want but it's torture
it's a torture program secondly torture
is a slippery slope you know those guys
you work with you know what's going to
happen somebody's going to kill a
prisoner in custody and then going to be
a congressional investigation and then
there's going to be a Justice Department
investigation and somebody's going to go
to prison do you want to go to prison
and I said no I don't want to go to
prison well it turned out I'm the only
one who went to
prison but at the time I said no no I
don't want to go to prison so I went
back down to the counterterrorism center
and I said this is a torture program and
I don't want to have anything to do with
it so I was because I had said no I was
not read into this special compartment
right only special people got to read
the cables that were coming in from this
secret location where Abu abuaba was
being held in the meantime I got
promoted on the strength of the abua
operation and I became the executive
assistant to the deputy director of the
CIA now in that capacity I was supposed
to have had access to every cable that
was coming in every operation around the
world it's it's really a very prized
position
but I was cut out of this torture
program it turned out most everybody was
cut out of the torture program so what I
was seeing in general classified traffic
was beginning on August the 1st 2002 the
CIA its contractors two psychologist
contractors began torturing Abu
Zeda they said for example by the time
they got to water boarding and we'll get
into that in a second that they water
boarded him once he had cracked he had
provided actionable intelligence that
saved American lives and disrupted
future terrorist attacks right that was
a
lie that was the lie that was put into
General traffic knowing that eventually
if something was going to leak it was
going to be that if something was going
to be passed to the Congressional
oversight committees it was going to be
that in the back channels the eyes only
channels and we now know this thanks to
the release of the Senate torture
report they waterboarded abua 83
times he went into
convulsions he vomited repeatedly he
begged them to stop and he provided no
actionable intelligence that led to no
disruptions of terrorist attacks and
saved no American lives interestingly
enough the CIA leaders from the period
um responsible for the torture program
recently came out with a book in which
they said that the Senate torture report
is just simply factually incorrect
despite the fact that the torture report
is based on primary source original CIA
documentation I would pause it to you
that they are the
Liars because torture is their legacy
when they die and their obituaries are
written the obituaries aren't going to
say this great Patriot died this great
champion of Freedom died it's going to
say this architect of our ill-advised
and illegal torture program died and so
they believe that if they keep repeating
this lie over and over and over again
that people either will be too stupid or
too gullible or too lazy to do their own
research and will believe that torture
worked I can tell you that it did not
not work there's an FBI agent by the
name of Ali
sufan Ali and I work together in
Pakistan and as soon as Abu Zeda was
captured Ali was sent out to the secret
prison where Abu Zeda was being
interrogated now it pains me believe me
it pains me in my gut to complement the
FBI but they are really good at
interrogations really good you don't
even realize you're being
interrogated and what Ali did was he sat
across the table from abuaba once abuaba
had recovered enough to be able to sit
and have a meeting with somebody he
offered him a date or a fig or an apple
or whatever it was and they had a
conversation over a period of weeks Abu
Zeda opened up to Ali and did provide
actionable intelligence that led to the
disruption of terrorist attacks
particularly in
Europe but the CIA didn't like the fact
that the FBI suddenly had Primacy in
this case especially because the Loc was
overseas and the CIA is always supposed
to be the primary agency overseas while
the FBI is the primary agency in the
United States so George tenant didn't
like this one bit and he went to
President Bush and he said I want the
CIA to have Primacy I want you to order
the FBI out and the president said
okay and he ordered the FBI out II
returned to Washington within 24 hours
the CIA began torturing Abu AA and he
stopped talking and never started
talking talking
again the core issue here is one of
Ethics there is no such thing as ethics
training in the in the CIA when you
enter the CIA you either have your own
ethical standards your own moral
background or you don't now couple this
with what I'm about to tell you a CIA
psychiatrist told me one time that the
CIA actively seeks to hire people with
sociopathic tendencies not
sociopaths sociopaths have no conscience
they're unable to feel empathy and they
can very easily pass a polygraph exam
because they're they're unable to feel
guilt okay they don't want sociopaths
because sociopaths are hard to manage
they tend to go out on their own but
people with sociopathic tendencies feel
comfortable working in moral ethical or
legal gray
areas and I'll admit to you you you know
when my bosses have come to me or had
come to me in the past and said Hey
listen what are you doing tomorrow and
I'd say oh nothing much okay we want you
to break into this house and plan a bug
I'd say okay and I'd break into the
house and plant a bug or plant a camera
or you know steal some documents or
whatever that was the job I had no
problem breaking into places I actually
kind of enjoyed it you get a little
adrenaline rush and then you think you
know USA USA right we're the good guys
we
thought well let me ask you something
about ethics this is something that I
often pose to uh to University students
college students because I think that
this really encapsulates the idea of
ethics and intelligence operations let's
say that you are CIA case officers and
you're working in the Middle East on a
counterterrorism issue and you have
recruited a major penetration of a
foreign terrorist group Hezbollah Isis
Al-Qaeda whatever it is and this guy is
giving you real information that's
allowing you to disrupt these attacks so
you're meeting with him in a hotel
somewhere in the Middle East and at the
start of the meeting he says to you look
I've done everything you wanted I've
given you all this private secret
information now you're going to do
something for me I want you to go out
and I want you to get me a prostitute
right now and if you don't I'm not going
to cooperate with you anymore how many
people here would get him the
prostitute yeah sure he's a scumbag but
your your job is to work with scumbags
right so yeah sure you'd get in the
prostitute what if he asks for a child
prostitute absolutely not absolutely
positively not I would tell him hey you
think you're the only game in town you
think you're the only person we have
that's infiltrated this group now he may
be but it's a child we're talking about
the sad point of this is that there's no
there's no guideline for this kind of
thing there are no
rules I can tell you firsthand that I've
worked with people who would go out and
get the child prostitute without giving
it 5 Seconds of thought because it's not
something that you have to cable back to
headquarters and ask permission for you
just go out and do it right we're
supposed to be professionals we're
supposed to be operations officers we're
supposed to be the the tip of the spear
as they say The Cutting Edge of American
foreign
policy but you lose your
humanity and then there's nobody to tell
you you're losing your
Humanity this was a serious problem that
I had at the
CIA it's a serious ongoing problem at
the
CIA now besides the fact that the
torture program was immoral and
unethical I maintained from the very
beginning beginning that it was illegal
we have something in our country called
the federal torture act the federal
torture act has been on the books for
many many years and it specifically
defines and then specifically bans
torture to put it in a nutshell it bans
anything that makes a person physically
uncomfortable or it bans anything done
on behalf of the American government by
a private person that makes a person
uncomfortable so clearly all of these
these 10 uh techniques were
illegal there were two midlevel Justice
Department officials at the time John U
and J
BBY and they somehow were able to turn
the law on its
head
Allah what does the word is
mean uh and they somehow concluded that
because Al-Qaeda Fighters were not State
actors they were not representatives of
any one country that they somehow were
not allowed the protections of the
Geneva Convention in addition to the
fact that the torture techniques were
not torture they were enhanced
interrogation techniques right different
terminology so that means it must be
different I've even given the CIA the
benefit of the doubt I've never called
for the prosecution of CIA officer who
believed they were acting within the law
by carrying out these torture techniques
but again we know from both the Senate
torture report and the CIA inspector
General's report that CIA officers went
far beyond what the justice department
ever approved for example on the first
day that Abu Zeda was tortured he was
subjected to a technique called Walling
Walling is
where the prisoner has a a rolled up
towel around his neck or one of those
sleep pillows around his neck and he's
grabbed by the lapels or by the shirt
and he's slammed against a wall now the
technique says in in the rules in the
memo from the justice department that
the wall must be made of plywood so that
there's a little bit of give and the
Prisoner doesn't get a skull injury well
on his very first day the Walling
technique was used with Abu Zeda oh but
they forgot to put the towel around his
neck and the wall was made of con
rete why wasn't that officer prosecuted
there was a prisoner by the name of
Hassan
ghoul Hassan gou turned out to be
innocent of
anything as many many prisoners were
especially at Guantanamo but hen ghoul
was subjected to a torture technique
called the cold
cell so the prisoner is stripped naked
he's chained to an eyebolt in the
ceiling so he can't move and he can't
get comfortable the cell is chilled to
50° and every hour somebody goes into
the cell and throws a bucket of ice
water on
him after about four hours of that
Hassan goul
died but nobody was ever prosecuted for
killing Hassan
ghoul what about Mahar arar has anybody
ever heard of Mahar orar Mahar arar was
a professor at a university in Canada he
had been in Europe he was flying back to
Toronto via JFK in New York when the
plane landed in JFK two FBI a agents
went on board and took him off the plane
they wouldn't tell him why they took him
off the plane he was turned over to
another government agency that has never
been
identified and Mahar was flown to Syria
where he was tortured mercilessly for
the next 18
months finally after 18 months the
syrians came back to us and said we
think this is the wrong
guy and so we said said okay let him
go he sued the American government his
suit was dismissed with prejudice on
National Security grounds meaning if the
CIA is forced to defend thems themselves
they'll have to reveal classified
information and they can't do that
because we need to protect National
Security right so the suit was dismissed
I spoke with Mahar last year he told me
he has not been able to leave his house
in 10 years he has such severe
post-traumatic stress disorder he did
Sue the Canadian government and they
gave him a settlement of $6 million but
he said they took my life I mean what do
I do with $6 million I can't leave my
house he'll never work again and we've
not even
apologized there's a second man by the
name of Khaled al-masri anybody ever
heard of khed almasri sure khed Alm was
a German citizen of Egyptian origin he
was a green grosser he owned a fruit and
vegetable stand now the name m is Arabic
for the Egyptian so it's just khed the
Egyptian right it's there must be 10
million people named khed Al in in Egypt
well KH Al M had a fight with his wife
and he decided he needed a break so he
got on a bus and decided to visit his
brother in
Macedonia in the
meantime a separate government
agency uh intercepted some
Communications indic that an
Egyptian a m named khed was going to
blow up the American Embassy in Toronto
Albania and so some genius
said it's this guy khed alasi because
remember nobody in the CIA speaks Arabic
right so the CIA talks a host government
into stopping this bus in the middle of
nowhere KH is removed from the bus and
he is has secretly flown to Egypt to be
tortured for the next 10
months again the Egyptians come to us
and say listen we've done everything to
this guy we think this is the wrong guy
and it was the wrong guy but when Hal Al
was finally released and sent back to
Germany he had a beard down to he he's
carrying a Quran and now he's a True
Believer we created that
fundamentalist that was our fault we did
it on purpose
well this is typical of what happens
inside the cia's counterterrorism center
there was this feeling that we had so
dropped the ball on
911 that we had the blood of 3,000
Americans on our hands that we were
going to do absolutely everything in our
power to make sure that that never
happened again even if what we were
doing was immoral illegal or unethical
and there was no oversight
that's what has
happened uh to our country since
September 11th one of my attorneys
jesselyn Rak who's a famed whistleblower
in her own right has said over the years
all I want is my September 10th country
back you know politics tends to be
cyclical it's it's a pendulum and it
swings back and forth well on September
11th it went like this and it's been
stuck there ever
since LW
that would have seemed insane to us 15
years ago are now the norm NSA which
from the the date of its creation was
prohibited from ever collecting any
information on American citizens now has
its primary mission to collect
information on American
citizens we have a program where the
president can order the deaths by drone
strike of American citizens overseas who
have never been accused of a crime who
have never confronted their accusers in
court and who have never had the
opportunity to defend
themselves we just kill them if we don't
like their
politics and then in the most recent
case we kill their children and then say
oh that that one was an
accident my life changed and not
necessarily for the better on December
17th I think it was 2007 Brian Ross of
ABC News called me and said that he had
a source who said that I had tortured
abua I said that was absolutely untrue I
had never tortured Abu Zeda or anyone
else I've never laid a hand on him or
anyone else and in fact I was the only
person who was kind to abuaba I said
your source is either mistaken or he's a
liar well he said an old reporter's
trick you're welcome to come on the show
and defend yourself I said I'll think
about it
meanwhile that same week President Bush
gave a press conference in which he said
we do not
torture my wife saw it at the same time
I did she was also a senior Cia officer
we looked at each other and I said he's
a bald-faced
liar four days later in response to a
reporter's question he said if there is
torture it's the result of a rogue CIA
officer and I thought oh my God they're
going to try to pin this on me
so I called Brian Ross and I said I'll
give you your interview and I made a
determination to myself that whatever
Brian Ross asked me I was going to tell
the truth to tell you the truth um when
I resigned from the CIA in 2004 I really
did walk away from these issues I just
didn't really pay any attention anymore
but I was vaguely aware that um Human
Rights Watch What Human Rights Watch had
issued a report in 2005 saying that the
CIA was torturing prisoners and in 2006
Amnesty International came out with a
report saying the same thing so in my
mind the information was out there well
Brian Ross asked me are we torturing our
prisoners and I said three things that
have just utterly changed the course of
my life I said the CIA was torturing its
prisoners torture was official US
government policy it was not a rogue and
that policy was approved by and signed
by the president himself so I did call
the president a bald-faced liar
right to his
face the next day the FBI began
investigating me and they investigated
me for an entire year and then they
determined in December 2008 after the
presidential election but before
President Obama's Inauguration they
determined that I had not committed a
crime and they closed the
case three months later John Brennan an
old Nemesis of mine from when we were
both analysts together
asked the justice department to reopen
the case I had no idea I was under
investigation
again they investigated me for another
three
years and then in January 2012 I was
arrested and charged with three counts
of Espionage one count of violating the
intelligence identities protection act
of 1981 I'm only the second American
ever to be charged with that and a
felony account of making a false
statement and my attorneys and I were
never exactly clear on what exactly the
false statement was supposed to be it
was thrown out anyway um but Espionage I
mean this is the gravest crime in
American can be charged with this a
potential death penalty uh
crime so the three counts were based on
this uh on one I had given the New York
Times top secret code word information
that was Declassified solely for the
purpose of Prosecuting me and that
information
was that after the September 11th
attacks the CIA had a program to kill or
capture members of
al-Qaeda top
secret the other two counts were just as
ridiculous uh this same New York Times
Reporter called me and said he was doing
a story on a CIA officer who had been
overt his entire career never Undercover
on LinkedIn CIA
analyst yeah I mean his email is like
CIA guy aol.com
seriously so he says can you introduce
me to this guy I said you know I haven't
seen him in years but I have a business
card he had resigned from the agency
years before he went to work for a
consulting firm I said he gave me his
business card so I scanned the business
card and I sent it to him and I sent it
to another reporter I was charged with
two counts of Espionage for those two
emails now we challenged those counts of
Espionage in court and my attorney said
your honor you know this is the result
of Mr kyaku faxing a business card uh to
a reporter an unclassified business card
for an for an overt employee and the
judge says well I find that very hard to
believe and she says to the
prosecutor you know Mr I don't even
remember his name I think I just blocked
it out on purpose some kind of
psychological defense mechanism Mr
whatever his name was and he stands up
and he says well well your honor Mr
kyaku should have known better that even
if it was unclassified he shouldn't have
been talking to the
press and the judge
said but Mr kiraku has a First Amendment
right to freedom of
speech well yes but she said I'll
entertain a motion to uh dismiss the
Espionage charges and they were
dismissed but this whole process dragged
da for a very long
time and my attorneys uh wanted to be
paid so I sold everything I had I had a
little piece of Beach property gone uh
all my stocks and bonds gone I sold all
my personal possessions on eBay and I
gave my attorneys $150,000 remember my
wife was fired the day I was arrested
just because she was married to me she
had a stellar CIA career so we were both
unemployed and um I said well how much
do I owe you guys they said you owe us
another $880,000
and this was like you know
September so I said if we go to trial
how much am I going to owe you they said
another million perhaps 2 million in
addition to the
880 so my wife and I sat down with a
calculator and we tried to figure this
out it became an economic decision but
this is the Justice Department's goal
this is the plan the plan is to bankrupt
you what they do is this thing called
stacking where instead of charging you
with a crime they'll charge you with
five crimes or 10 or 20 like they did to
Tom Drake or Jeffrey Sterling or like
they're trying to do with Ed Snowden and
what they do is they bankrupt you and
they get you to the point where you're
desperate and you'll do anything to make
this case go away and so they come back
and they say well will drop all the
charges but one if you plead
guilty so do I roll the dice remember
I'm looking at 45 years I'm I'm 51 I'll
die in prison there's no federal parole
thanks to Ronald Reagan's get tough on
crime nonsense from the 80s so do I roll
the dice knowing that the justice
department wins 98.2% of its cases
according to prop
publica um you know we used to have a
joke at the CIA s Hussein I worked on
Iraq most of my career Saddam Hussein
would win 98% of his presidential uh in
his presidential races and we would
laugh and we'd say the fixes in and the
justice department wins 98% of our cases
and we say wow they're
Geniuses never understood
that so do you roll the dice knowing
that you have a 1.8% chance of success
or do you just take the take the plea
and make the thing go away one of my
attorneys the the one who I who I
admired and respected most pulled me
aside one day and he
said if you were my brother I would beg
you to take this deal this can be a blip
in your life or it can be the defining
event of your life let it be the
blip and so they offered me 30 months
I'd be out in less than two I took the
deal in fact it was a little bit
embarrassing because on the day of my
sentencing I had to stand up and the
judge said uh how do you plead and I
said I changed my plea to guilty and she
said do you admit that you committed
this crime uh purposefully and I said no
I do not it was an accident and she said
to my attorney you need to consult with
your client and my attorney leans over
and he says you have to say you did it
on purpose and I said but I didn't do it
on purpose and he said I know but you
have to say that you did because that's
the only way you get the deal I said
sure I did it on purpose and she says
Okay I accept your plea guilty
sentencing is in three months
but that's our justice department you
know I hadn't committed Espionage but in
the eastern district of Virginia they
would convict a baloney sandwich
especially when the jury is made up of
people from the CIA the FBI DOD and
every defense contractor in
Washington what are your chances I'll
tell you one more thing about that too I
laugh now but it made me cry back then
um my best friend's wife has an uncle
who is the top jury consultant in
America OJ Simpson jury William Kennedy
Smith George Zimmerman all the biggest
uh uh trials so he flew up to Washington
and he said because you're Rich's nephew
uh I'm going to do this for free so we
had him get a security clearance we we
read him into the case and he came back
and he said if we were in any other
District in America we win this but the
eastern district of Virginia he said you
you don't have a prayer they don't call
it the Espionage court for nothing and
interestingly enough I read later that
no defendant in a national security case
has ever won in the eastern district of
Virginia I stayed up all night with my
wife the night before I decided to take
the plea I was supposed to go to court
at something like 10:00 in the morning
and at 7 I sent a letter to my attorneys
saying Heather and I had been up all
night and we decided we're going to go
to trial I haven't done anything wrong
and I'm going to
fight
and the next thing I knew they arrived
at the house and that's when we had the
blip versus defining event conversation
and he said you don't get it you can't
win we're beyond the the question of of
guilt or innocence guilt or innocence
doesn't matter